# RAJATH JAIPRAKASH

🜎 rajathjn | 🛅 rajath-jaiprakash | 🏶 Portfolio | 🗷 rajathjnx@gmail.com | 🖫 +91-9900852849

# Summary

Site Reliability Engineer II with 3 years of specialized experience in Infrastructure Automation, CI/CD, and Logging/Monitoring pipelines. Achieved over 50% reduction in manual operations by designing and implementing 20+ Ansible roles across production environments. Specialized in building Automation and proven contributor in cross team collaborations.

### Skills

**Programming:** Python, Shell Scripting, C++, Powershell Scripting

Tools & Technologies: Ansible, Elasticsearch (ELK stack), Docker, GitHub Actions, Jenkins, Syslog-ng, Telegraf, In-

fluxDB, Grafana, Prometheus, NagiosXI, OpenSNMP, vSphere, ESXi, KVM Currently Upskilling: Kubernetes, OpenTelemetry, OpenNMS, Terraform

Certifications: The Linux Foundation: LFS162, Red Hat Certified Engineer (EX294)

# Work Experience

## Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer 2

Oct 2024 - Present

- Architected end-to-end **CI/CD pipelines** for our Access Border Routers by integrating it with our AAA Simulators and custom deployment scripts in collaboration with our QA team, making the process **4x** faster and reduced our downtime to just **30 seconds**.
- Engineered fault-tolerant system by developing **Python** based auto-remediation scripts for **8 critical services**, significantly reduced manual recovery procedures and improved service availability.
- Identified, Troubleshot and Solved a Business critical logging incident which impacted our **6WIND VSRs**, across **18 Distributed Edge sites**.

#### Akamai Technologies | Site Reliability Engineer

July 2022 - Oct 2024

- Improved our deployment workflow by crafting **20+ Ansible** roles for automated configuration management, reducing deployment errors and cutting rollout time from days to hours across **4 environments**.
- Executed the complex migration of **18 production logging servers** by designing comprehensive transition plan and implementing parallel cutover strategy, maintaining near **100%** service availability and processing over **250K+ daily transactions** without interruption.
- Revamped our logging infrastructure by optimizing, migrating and upgrading our **ELK Clusters** to efficiently handle **150 GB** of daily logs each, resulting in a **300**% increase in log search performance and enabling real-time anomaly detection for **20+ critical services**.
- Spearheaded DevOps knowledge sharing initiative by conducting 6 technical workshops for 30+ engineers over 3 different time-zones, resulting in 40% fewer deployment-related incidents across development teams.
- Enhanced monitoring for 200+ nodes by implementing hierarchical alerting structure in NagiosXI using InfluxDB and OpenSNMP Collector, reducing false positives and redundant alerts by 70%.

#### Projects

## ClipForge - AI Driven Video Processing Pipeline

- Engineered an end-to-end local and open-source automated video generation pipeline by integrating WhisperX, FFm-peg, and AI agents created using Langchain Python. Project has received over 77k+ impressions to date.
- Built AI-based metadata generation, improving **SEO** and content discoverability by **40%**. Implemented automated **CI/CD** testing via **GitHub Actions**.
- Deployed on **Dockerized** Ubuntu containers with real-time **Discord** notification system, supporting 100+ daily video operations.

# Education

## PES University, Bangalore

2018 - 2022

B.Tech in Electronics and Communication Engineering B.Tech Minors in Computer Science and Engineering GPA: 8.99/10